Guide to the Frank Espada photographs and papers, 1946-2010 and undated, bulk 1975-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frank Espada photographs and papers 1946-2010 and undated bulk 1975-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Espada, Frank, 1930-
45.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 16,441 Items
Political activist and documentary photographer of Puerto Rican extraction based in California. Collection consists largely of photographic prints, contact sheets, proofs, and negatives, chiefly dating from the mid-1970s through 2010, relating to Espada's Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project, his project work on indigenous Chamorro communities in Micronesia, primarily in Guam, Tinian, and Saipan, and his documentary work on HIV/AIDS outreach and education in San Francisco. The Puerto Rican Diaspora materials include over 100 oral history recordings. A smaller group of photographic and manuscript materials derive from Espada's participation in the Civil Rights Movement on behalf of voter registration and school desegregation in New York City, 1962-1970. Other materials include research files on documentary topics he was currently investigating; materials related to photography project exhibits; teaching materials from his photography courses; and other manuscript and printed materials from his career. Acquired by the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.00367
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Online Items
Images from this collection have been digitized and are available in: Frank Espada Photographs - Duke Digital Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Frank Espada photographs and papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 2010-2013.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1930 Born, Utuado, Puerto Rico
1939 Emigrated with his family to New York City
1952 Married Marilyn Espada
Late 1950s Studied photography at the New York Institute of Photography and with Gene Smith
1967 Joined the City-Wide Puerto Rican Development Program
1979-1981 Received National Endowment for the Humanities grant to carry out the Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project, which resulted in a book and 45 exhibits over a 15-year period
1985-2010 Taught photography courses and workshops in San Francisco, California
1989-1990 Worked with Mid-City Coalition for HIV Prevention in San Francisco, documenting the work of the community organizers
1990-1992 Undertook the Chamorro Documentary Project, documenting life for indigenous peoples in Micronesia
2006 Published The Puerto Rican Diaspora: Themes in the Survival of a People
2008 Received an honorary Doctor of Arts degree from Lehman College, Bronx, New York
Espada's documentary photographs have been exhibited around the world: at the Museum of Art in Chicago; Museo del Barrio, New York City; Honolulu Hale; and the Museo de Arte in Ponce, Puerto Rico, among others.
Collection Overview
The Frank Espada Papers and Photographs collection consists largely of photographic prints, contact sheets, proofs, and negatives, chiefly dating from the mid-1970s through 2010, relating to Espada's Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project, his project work on indigenous Chamorro communities in Micronesia, primarily in Guam, Tinian, and Saipan, and his work documenting HIV/AIDS outreach and education in San Francisco. The largest body of materials, which includes photographs as well as manuscripts and recorded interviews, derives from Espada's work with the Puerto Rican communities which spanned several decades. A smaller group of materials, nineteen prints, associated contacts and negatives and several folders of documents, were created through Espada's activism in the Civil Rights Movement for voter registration and school desegregation in New York City from 1962-1970.
Other materials include research files on documentary topics he was currently investigating; materials used in preparation for his many photography project exhibits, large and small; teaching syllabi and notes from his photography courses; awards and memorabilia; and other manuscript and printed materials from his career in photography.
The photographic materials have been arranged in series according to format: Contact Sheets and Prints; Negatives; Loose Proofs; Manuscript Materials; Photographic Prints; and Audiovisual Materials. there is also an oversize materials grouping at the end of the collection.
Acquired by the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Espada, Frank, 1930-; Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project; AIDS (Disease) -- United States -- Prevention -- Pictorial works; Chamorro (Micronesian people) -- Pictorial works; Civil rights movements -- United States; Documentary photography; Indigenous peoples -- Pictorial works; Photography of immigrants; Portrait photography; Puerto Ricans -- Pictorial works; Puerto Ricans -- United States; Puerto Ricans -- United States -- Social conditions; Guam -- Pictorial works; Hawaii -- Puerto Ricans -- Pictorial works; Micronesia -- Pictorial works; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- 1951-; New York (N.Y.) -- Puerto Ricans -- Pictorial works; Pennsylvania -- Puerto Ricans -- Pictorial works; Puerto Rico -- Pictorial works; Audiocassettes; Contact sheets; Gelatin silver prints; Oral histories; Negatives (photographic); Vintage prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Preliminary Description of Collection
- Contact Sheets and Proofs, 1964-1992, (15 boxes)
  Houses Frank Espada's contact sheets and proofs from his work on the Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project, the Chamorro Documentary Project, and his projects documenting San Francisco's Youth Environment Study (YES) in 1989-1990, the Civil Rights Movement in 1964, along with other various small projects. These have been sorted into contact sheets and proofs, arranged by project and then by location or number, using a numbering scheme developed by Espada that reaches across his negatives and contact sheets.
  Negatives have been removed to their own non-circulating boxes, beginning at Box 16.
  These are not the only proofs present in the collection. There is also a series of Loose Proofs that have not been sleeved, but have been sorted by project. Refer to the Detailed Description for more information on that series.
  In addition, a third series in the collection contains Prints from several of Espada's projects.
  - Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project
    The photographs from the Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project were taken in over 30 locations throughout the United States and Puerto Rico. They have been grouped according to location, using Espada's own numbering scheme to help connect negatives to contact sheets. Missing numbers have been noted below each heading. Most proofs have only a location or event designation, with no matching numbers accompanying the image. Locations including California, Milwaukee, Hawaii, Puerto Rico, New York, Pennsylvania, Connecticut, and Washington, D.C. Most locations have sub-groups that are listed in greater detail below. Bulk dates from the project range from 1979-1981, with some as early as 1976.
    - California, May 1981 (Box 1)
      - Contact sheets, CA 1-32 (Box 1)
        Missing CA-16, 18, 19, 21, 24, 25, 30, 31.
      - Proofs (Box 1)
    - Dia de San Juan, Cabrillo Beach, California, 1976
      - Contact sheets 1-12 (Box 1)
      - Proofs (Box 1)
    - Chicago, August 1982
      - Contact sheets, CH 1-37 (Box 1)
        Missing CH 2, 7, 10, 24.
      - Proofs, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 1)
      - Proofs, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Hartford, Connecticut, 1982
      - Proofs, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Prints (Box 2)
        17 8.5x11 Black and White vintage prints.
    - Hawaii, April 1981
      Scenes include Kona, Kohala, a macadamia farm, Kukuihaele, Honolulu, Shinko House (Honolulu), a Puerto Rican Softball League, Hilo, and Kalihi Valley.
      - Contact sheets, HI 1-39 (Box 2)
        Missing HI 28, 32, 25.
      - Contact sheets, HI 40-71 (Box 3)
        Missing HI 44, 48, 52, 68.
      - Proofs, April 1981
        - Kohala farmers (Box 3)
        - Kona farmers (Box 3)
        - Santos Caravalho (Box 3)
        - Shinko House (Box 3)
        - Johnny Matias (Box 3)
        - Puerto Rican Softball League (Box 3)
        - Various subjects, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 3)
        - Various subjects, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Milwaukee, 1983
      - Contact sheets, 1-12 (Box 4)
    - Vineland and Glassboro, New Jersey (CATA), 1981
      - Contact sheets, GL 1-15 (Box 4)
    - New York, 1980-1981
      - Ballet Hispanico, January 1981
        - Contact sheets, NY 1-28 (Box 4)
        - Contact sheets, NY 134-140 (Box 4)
          Missing NY 135.
        - Proofs, (1-2 of 4 folders) (Box 4)
        - Proofs, (3-4 of 4 folders) (Box 5)
      - Puerto Rican Travelling Theatre, January 1981
        - Contact sheets, NY 29-37 (Box 5)
        - Proofs (Box 5)
      - Museo del Barrio, 3 Kings Day, 1981
        - Contact sheets, NY 38-54 (Box 5)
        - Proofs (Box 5)
      - East Harlem Music School, December 1980-1981 (Box 6)
        - Contact sheets, NY 55-67 (Box 6)
          Missing NY 62.
        - Proofs, (3 folders) (Box 6)
      - PROMESA, South Bronx, 1980-1981
        - Contact sheets, NY 68-100 (Box 6)
        - Proofs, (3 folders) (Box 6)
      - Manhattan Valley, 1981 (Box 7)
        - Contact sheets, NY 102-110, NY 141-156 (Box 7)
        - Proofs, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - Boricua College, January 1989
        - Contact sheets, NY 111-118 (Box 7)
      - United Bronx Parents, MLK Memorial, South Bronx, March 1981
        - Contact sheets, NY 119-132 (Box 7)
        - Proofs (Box 7)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 8)
      - Harrisburg and Lancaster, December 1979
        - Contact sheets, PRD 20, 22-25 (Box 8)
      - Pennsylvania, June 1981
        Includes Harrisburg, Lancaster, Reading, Avondale, and Kennett Square.
        - Contact sheets, PA 1-32 (Box 8)
          Missing PA 10.
        - Contact sheets, PA 33-65 (Box 8)
          Missing PA 53-58, 61, 63.
        - Contact sheets, PA 66-88 (Box 8)
          Missing PA 71, 73, 83.
    - Planning Grant
      - Milwaukee, 1979
        - Contact sheets, PRD 1-6 (Box 8)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities, December 1979-May 1980
        - Contact sheets, 7-47 (Box 8)
          Excluding 12, 13, 20, 22-25, 42.
        - Contact sheets, 49-75 (Box 8)
          Missing 50, 74.
        - Contact sheets, 76-95 (Box 8)
    - El Puente-A Documentary, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, 1984 (Box 9)
      - Contact sheets, 1-25 (Box 9)
    - Puerto Rico-Returning Migrants, 1981
      - Contact sheets, 2-49 (Box 9)
        Missing 1, 7, 16, 29.
      - Contact sheets, 50-92 (Box 9)
      - Proofs, (1-3 of 8 folders) (Box 9)
      - Proofs, (4-8 of 8 folders) (Box 10)
    - Puerto Rican Legal Defense Fund, 1982 (Box 11)
      - Contact sheets, PRLD 1-10, 17-36, 2C, 5C-10C (Box 11)
    - Hispanic Festival, Washington, DC, 1982
      - Contact sheets, DC 1-34 (Box 11)
  - Other Projects, 1962-1991 and undated
    This subseries includes contact sheets, proofs, and some prints for a range of smaller projects undertaken by Espada, including his photography from the Civil Rights movement and voter registration in New York, 1962-1970, and the HIV/AIDS crisis in San Francisco.
    - Joey Benko, San Francisco, CA, 1991
      - Contact sheets, C/S 1-6, 13, 14 (Box 11)
      - 5x7 proofs (Box 11)
    - Humphrey Garrett and Family, Oakland, CA, 1992
      - Contact sheets, C/S 10-12, 15-20 (Box 11)
      - 5x7 prints (Box 11)
    - Civil Rights, New York, 1962-1970
      - Contact sheets, CR 1-33 (Box 11)
        Missing CR 5.
    - East New York Action, undated
      - Proofs (Box 11)
    - ISH Campaign and Food Service, Betancourt Lunch Program and Campaign, South Bronx, New York, June 1981
      - Contact sheets, 1-26 (Box 11)
        Missing 10, 11, 13-17, 20, 23.
    - O.S.Y. Youth Project, HIV/AIDS Prevention, San Francisco, 1989 (Box 12)
      - Contact sheets, OSY 1-38 (Box 12)
      - Proofs (Box 12)
    - Quest International, Berkeley, Esperanza, and San Jose, CA, June 1986
      - Contact sheets, unnumbered (Box 12)
      - 8x10 prints (Box 12)
    - Real Alternatives Program (RAP), The Mission, San Francisco, 1985-1986
      - Contact sheets, 1-30 (Box 12)
    - SAJA Benefit, Strawberry Hill, Robert Kennedy estate, Washington, DC, Summer 1979
      - Contact sheets, 4-16 (Box 12)
    - Solivan's Campaign for State Assembly, East Harlem, New York, October 1974
      - Contact sheets, 1-12 (Box 12)
        Missing Number 7.
    - SRO Project, Mission Agenda, San Francisco, CA, 1997
      - Contact sheets, SRO 1-18 (Box 12)
        Missing SRO 4.
      - 5x7 inch proofs (Box 12)
    - Voter Registration, Brownsville, New York, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Contact sheets, 1-6 (Box 13)
      - Proofs (Box 13)
    - Youth Environment Study (YES), San Francisco, 1989-1990
      - HIV/AIDS Prevention Program
        - Contact sheets, 1-44 (Box 13)
          Missing Number 6.
        - Contact sheets, 45-96 (Box 13)
          Missing Numbers 51, 53, 73, 79-83, 85
      - Sex for Crack
        - Contact sheets, 1-6 (Box 13)
      - YES Project, Other Materials
        - Proofs, 1990-1992 (Box 13)
        - Prints, 8x10 inches, 1990, (42 items) (Box 13)
  - Chamorro Documentary Project
    Contact sheets and proofs from Espada's documentary project on the indigenous Chamorro people, focusing on Micronesia, primarily Guam, Tinian, and Saipan, 1990. Also includes a set of several hundred images on contact sheets, taken during a festival in support of Chamorro people, held in Vallejo, California in 1989.
    - Chamorro Festival, Vallejo, Calif., 1989 July (Box 14)
      - Contact sheets, 1-10 (Box 14)
    - Micronesia, 1990 (Box 14)
      - Contact sheets, 1-50 (Box 14)
        Missing Numbers 29-32.
      - Contact sheets, 51-99 (Box 14)
        Missing Numbers 90-96.
      - Contact sheets, 100-144 (Box 14)
      - Contact sheets, 145-192 (Box 14)
        Missing 153, 157, 167, 186-188.
      - Micronesia Proofs, (4 folders) (Box 15)
- Negatives Series, 1972-1992 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Arrangement parallels the arrangement of the contact sheets and proofs of the Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project, the Other Projects, and the Chamorro Documentary Project subseries.
  Original negatives are restricted to access and have been removed into non-circulating boxes for preservation purposes.
  - Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project Negatives (Box 16)
    - California, 1981: CA 1-32 (Box 16)
      Missing CA 3, 6, 16, 18-21, 24, 25, 30, 31.
    - Dia de San Juan, Cabrillo Beach, CA, 1976: 1-12 (Box 16)
    - Chicago, 1982: CH 1-37 (Box 16)
    - Hawaii, 1981: HI 1-39 (Box 16)
      Missing HI 10, 35.
    - Hawaii, 1981: HI 40-70 (Box 16)
      Missing HI 48, 52, 64, 68, 71.
    - Milwaukee, 1983: 1-12 (Box 16)
    - Vineland and Glassboro, New Jersey, 1981: GL 1-16 (Box 16)
      Missing GL 5.
    - New York-Ballet Hispanico, 1981: NY 1-28 (Box 16)
    - New York-Ballet Hispanico, 1981: NY 134-138 (Box 16)
      Missing 135, 139, 140.
    - New York-Puerto Rican Travelling Theatre, 1981: NY 29-37 (Box 17)
    - New York-Museo del Barrio, 1981: NY 38-54 (Box 17)
    - New York-East Harlem Music School, 1980-1981: NY 55-67 (Box 17)
    - New York-PROMESA, 1980-1981: NY 68-100 (Box 17)
    - New York-Manhattan Valley, 1981: NY 102-110 and NY 141-156 (Box 17)
      Missing 105, 142, 146, 148, 149.
    - New York-Boricua College, 1989: NY 112-118 (Box 17)
      Missing NY 117.
    - New York-United Bronx Parents, 1981: NY 119-133 (Box 17)
    - Pennsylvania: Harrisburg and Lancaster, 1979: PRD 20, 22-25 (Box 17)
    - Pennsylvania, 1981: PA 1-29 (Box 17)
    - Pennsylvania, 1981: PA 30-88 (Box 17)
      Missing PA 40, 53-58, 61, 63, 71, 73, 83.
    - Planning Grant, 1979: PRD 1-6 (Box 18)
    - Planning Grant, 1979-1980: PRD 8-43 (Box 18)
      Excluding PRD 7, 12, 13, 20, 22-25, 27, 42, 43.
    - Planning Grant, 1979-1980: PRD 44-95 (Box 18)
      Missing PRD 48, 50, 55, 72-75, 77, 79, 81, 84, 90, 91.
    - El Puente Documentary, 1984: 1-25 (Box 18)
    - Puerto Rico-Returning Migrants, 1981: 2-49 (Box 18)
      Missing 14, 16, 26.
    - Puerto Rico-Returning Migrants, 1981: 50-92 (Box 18)
      Missing 55, 66, 86, 87.
    - Puerto Rican Legal Defense Fund, 1982: PRLD 1-10, 17-36, 2C, 5C-10C (Box 18)
    - Washington, DC, 1982: DC 1-34 (Box 18)
  - Other Projects Subseries (Box 19)
    - Joey Benko: C/S 1-6, 13, 14 (Box 19)
    - Garrett Humphrey and Family: C/S 10-12, 15-20 (Box 19)
    - Civil Rights: CR 1-33 (Box 19)
      Missing CR 1-3, 8, 9, 13, 16, 26, 27.
    - ISH Campaign and Food Service: 1-26 (Box 19)
      Missing Numbers 11, 12.
    - O.S.Y. Youth Project: OSY 1-38 (Box 19)
      Missing OSY 4, 11, 15, 22, 23.
    - Real Alternatives Program (RAP): 1-30 (Box 19)
    - Solivan's Campaign: 1-12 (Box 19)
    - SRO Project: SRO 1-18 (Box 19)
    - YES-Sex for Crack: 1-6 (Box 20)
    - YES-HIV/AIDS Prevention: 1-45 (Box 20)
      Missing Numbers 6, 40.
    - YES-HIV/AIDS Prevention: 46-97 (Box 20)
      Missing 51, 53, 73, 80-82, 85.
  - Chamorro Documentary Project Negatives
    - Chamorro Festival, Vallejo, California, 1989 July: 1-10 (Box 20)
    - Micronesia, 1990: 1-50 (Box 20)
    - Micronesia, 1990: 51-118 (Box 20)
    - Micronesia, 1990: 119-192 (Box 20)
- Loose Proofs Series, 1980-1990 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Along with the sleeved proofs that have been filed with the contact sheets in the Contact Sheets and Proofs series (above), the collection contains thousands of loose proofs that are sorted by event or location, but have not been matched to a contact sheet or negative. This series includes proofs from the Puerto Rican Diaspora and the Chamorro Documentary projects, as well as miscellaneous, unlabelled proofs.
  Proofs have been sorted by project and location, and any accompanying information has been transcribed below. Each box contains smaller shoebox-style boxes of proofs, so container types are designated as 21.1, 21.2, and so on, to distinguish between the smaller boxes held within the larger containers.
  - Chamorro Documentary Project
    - At a friend's house (Box 21.1)
    - Documentation of Funeral of Ricardo Bordaleo, Former Governor of Guam, who committed suicide on February 1, 1990 (Box 21.1)
    - Agaña, Japanese town, 1990 (Box 21.1)
    - Japanese baseball players: training in Guam (Box 21.1)
    - Loling's family at Geri's (Box 21.1)
    - Loling's class (Box 21.1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21.1)
    - Saipan Party, (68 proofs) (Box 21.1)
    - Saipan Citizens Program (Box 21.1)
  - Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project
    - Boston, 1980 (Box 21.1)
    - Nick Arana, Boston, 1980 (Box 21.1)
    - Raquel Ortiz, La Plaza, Boston, 1980 (Box 21.1)
    - California
      - Los Angeles, Cabrillo, San Francisco, Oakland, 1981 (Box 21.1)
      - Los Angeles, Cabrillo, San Francisco, Oakland, 1981 (Box 21.2)
      - Oakland, 1980 (Box 21.2)
      - Argunzoni, Los Angeles (Box 21.2)
      - Doña Lila, Oakland, 1981 (Box 21.2)
      - San Francisco, 1980 (Box 21.2)
      - Edelmiro Huertas, San Francisco Pionero, May 1981 (Box 21.2)
  - O.S.Y. Project, San Francisco, 1986 (Box 21.2)
  - Real Alternatives Program, San Francisco, 1986 (Box 21.2)
  - Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project
    - California
      - Tom Chevere, San Francisco, 1981 (Box 21.2)
    - Chicago
      - Chicago, 1982 (Box 21.2)
      - Cha-Cha Jimenez, Chicago, 1980 (Box 21.2)
    - Cleveland (Box 21.2)
    - Hartford
      - Hartford Centro (Box 21.3)
      - Eugenio Caro, Hartford, 1981 (Box 21.3)
      - Savage N., Hartford, 1981 (Box 21.3)
    - Hawaii
      - Hawaii, 1980 (Box 21.3)
      - The Hawaiian Experience, 1980-1981 (Box 21.3)
      - The Hawaiian Experience, 1980-1981 (Box 21.4)
      - Hawaii, 1980-1981 (Box 21.4)
    - Lorain O., 1980 (Box 21.4)
    - Milwaukee, 1980 (Box 21.4)
    - New Jersey
      - ACLU Farmworkers Project (CATA), Glassboro, 1981 (Box 21.4)
      - CATA, Glassboro-Vineland, 1981, (125 proofs) (Box 21.4)
      - Eladio el Gallito, Jersey City, 1980 (Box 21.4)
      - Jersey City, Newark (Box 21.4)
    - New York
      - Ballet Hispanico, (175 proofs) (Box 21.5)
      - Ballet Hispanico, 1981, (175 proofs) (Box 21.5)
      - Ballet Hispanico, 1981 (Box 21.5)
      - Graduation, Boricua College, 1974 (Box 21.5)
      - Boricua College, 1980, (200 prints) (Box 21.5)
      - Boricua College, 1980, (100 prints) (Box 21.5)
      - Boricua College, 1980 (Box 21.5)
  - Ismael Betancourt
    - Political campaign, Latin Belly, South Bronx, 1975, (175 proofs) (Box 21.5)
    - Food Service Company, South Bronx, 1982 (Box 22.6)
    - Political campaign, Bronx, 1982 (Box 22.6)
  - Puerto Rican Diaspora Documentary Project
    - New York
      - Johnny Colon, East Harlem Free Music School, 1980 (Box 22.6)
      - Manhattan Valley (Box 22.6)
      - Manhattan Valley, 1981, (225 proofs) (Box 22.6)
      - Museo del Barrio, 3 Kings Day Parade, East Harlem (Box 22.6)
      - Museo del Barrio, 3 Kings Day Parade, East Harlem, 1981 January 6 (Box 22.6)
      - Puerto Rican Travelling Theatre, 1980, (60 proofs) (Box 22.6)
      - United Bronx Parents, MLK Memorial, Bronx, 1980, (175 proofs) (Box 22.6)
      - PROMESA, South Bronx, 1974, (775 proofs) (Box 22.7)
    - Pennsylvania
      - Flower nursery, Avondale, 1981 (Box 22.7)
      - Nursery, Avondale (Box 22.7)
      - Drug abuse prevention, Centro de Vida, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.7)
      - Grupo folklorico, Centro de Vida, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.7)
      - Grupo folklorico, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.7)
      - English class, Centro de Vida, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.7)
      - English as a second language, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.8)
      - ESL program, Centro de Vida, Harrisburg (Box 22.8)
      - ESL program, Centro de Vida, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.8)
      - ESL Program, Harrisburg, 1981 (Box 22.8)
      - Kennett Square (Box 22.8)
      - Angel Hernandez, Mushroom worker, Kennett Square (Box 22.8)
      - Mushrooms, Kennett Square, 1981 (Box 22.8)
      - Mushroom workers, Kennett Square (Box 22.8)
      - Skills training, Lancaster, 1980 (Box 22.8)
      - Bilingual class, Reading, 1980 (Box 22.8)
      - Bilingual program, Reading, 1980 (Box 22.8)
      - Bilingual program, Reading, 1981 (Box 22.8)
      - The Clock Lesson, Reading (Box 23.9)
    - Planning Grant
      - 1979-1980, (700 proofs) (Box 23.9)
    - Puerto Rico
      - 1981 (Box 23.9)
      - Returned Migrants, (725 proofs) (Box 23.9)
      - Returned Migrants (Box 23.10)
    - Washington, DC
      - Hispanic Festival (Box 23.10)
      - Hispanic Festival, (200 proofs) (Box 23.10)
      - Hispanic Festival, 1982, (75 proofs) (Box 23.10)
      - Solidarity, 1981 (Box 23.10)
      - Solidarity demonstration, 1981, (100 proofs) (Box 23.10)
      - Solidarity demonstration, 1981, (175 proofs) (Box 23.11)
  - Other Proofs
    - Various loose proofs, (900 items) (Box 23.11)
- Manuscript Materials Series, 1989-2005 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Espada's teaching career is documented in this series, which includes re-foldered class binders as well as evaluations, class rosters, handouts, and other course materials about photography. Original folder titles have been retained in most cases.